Over 300 years before the birth of
Christ, a 22year-old man embarked on a
meteoric campaign of conquest. By its
triumphant end, he was undisputed master
of an empire that stretched from the
Nile to the Indis. To his countrymen, he
was the embodiment of glory. A heroic
warrior in the classical mold. To his
soldiers, an inspiring leader who shared
the bitter hardships of constant
campaigning with unfl flagging energy.
To his courtiers, he was a descendant of
the Olympian gods worthy of worship as a
divine being. In the unfailing pursuit
of his destiny, he would shape the
history of the world. His name was
Alexander. To posterity, he would be
Alexander the Great.
Alexander the general. Alexander the
Builder, Alexander the Statesman,
Alexander the God. Behind the
achievements and legends was a restless
young man driven by an obsessive,
boundless ambition.
Alexander the man was a complex, at
times contradictory figure capable of
incredible generosity and savage
cruelty. He would plan a campaign in
meticulous detail and then risk
everything on a do or die charge.
Alexander was probably one of the
greatest generals of ancient times, if
not the greatest general. uh he managed
to combine extreme youth, he was only 32
or 33 when he died, with some of the
greatest feats that you can imagine a
general in those days could ever hope to
achieve.
To understand Alexander's ambitions and
accomplishments, we must first
understand the country of his birth and
the land of which it was part.
The Greek Empire was centered around the
citystates of thieves, Sparta, and
especially Athens. Athens was the
cultural center, but its thriving
business as a trading port also created
its wealth and power.
The Athenians were a seafaring nation
and they expanded their influence around
the Aian Sea. into Asia Minor where they
founded settlements and towns.
Gradually over the centuries, Athens had
come to dominate its neighbors.
Its democratic government was taken as a
model for the world. Its philosophers
and artists were an inspiration to all.
Although they would never admit it
openly, Athenian civilization was the
cultural pinnacle to which other Greek
states aspired. But beside the positive
things in life, there was also the
reverse side of the coin. Athens had
often become embroiled in a series of
bitter wars. The most notable of these
was the great pelipeneian war against
Sparta.
The cost of that particular war had been
defeat, dwindling wealth, loss of
manpower, and political subjugation.
Although, as it turned out, this setback
was only temporary, it produced a
situation ripe for exploitation by
outsiders.
The people to exploit it were the
Persians. Under the rule of the godlike
great king, the Persian Empire's
influence sprawled from Egypt to India.
The great king's territories were
divided into dependencies overseen by a
member of the royal family or nobility.
The great king's authority was absolute,
his royal palaces lavishly furnished,
and the royal treasuries packed with
fabulous wealth.
The great king used the disunityity
among the Greek citystates to expand his
domination of Asia Minor, including the
Athenian settlements on the Aian coast.
These intrusions were bad enough, but
the Athenians had a long historical
cause to resent the Persians.
150 years before Alexander, the great
Persian king Xerxes had swept through
mainland Greece. Athens had fallen, its
people were humiliated, and its temples
desecrated.
Although Xerxes was eventually defeated,
the sacking of their city left the
Athenians with a historical desire for
revenge.
But revenge needed strength. Real
strength demanded a united Greece
because only then could they elect a
captain general to lead their armies to
liberate Asia Minor.
By the year of Alexander's birth, 356
BC, it looked as if a suitable candidate
had appeared. The great man was
Alexander's father, Philip II of
Macedonia.
By a series of diplomatic treaties,
intermarriages, military victories, and
when necessary, political murders, King
Philip had united all Macedonia under
his rule. From his royal palace at PA,
he had begun a process of modernization
within the Macedonian army. His officers
were drawn from the nobility of the
Macedonian highlands. Rugged, warlike,
and fierce, these tribal leaders were
experienced fighting men. Macedonia had
long been a frontier between civilized
Greece and the world beyond.
Riding, hunting, drinking, and fighting
were the main interests of its tribal
rulers.
To the sophisticated Athenians,
Macedonian society was savage, feudal,
uncultured, and primitive. Its laws and
religion were barbaric by their
standards.
>> Curiously enough, to the Greeks, who
lived, of course, to the south of
Macedonia, he was a barbarian. He spoke
Greek with an accent as anyone did who
was outside Adica and the Palpine.
And yet Macedonia that he ruled was very
wealthy because he had the gold mines
there and he had silver mines.
>> But King Phillip was able to mold the
raw material of the Macedonian army into
a formidable professional fighting
force.
The military innovations of Philip and
Macedon
um have their roots in a period when he
was a teenager.
He was exiled from his own country and
he spent a period of several years in
thieves, the main city of Biosha
in the company of Theban generals who
had become who had made thieves the most
important fighting force in the whole of
Greece in the first part of the 4th
century before Christ. And here in
Thieves, the young Philillip learned the
new techniques of war, the benefits of
training, of standing armies, the
benefits of uniform equipment for all
members of the fighting force. and the
benefits of a fighting force which was
bonded by close personal ties so that
one man fought beside another
did not yield
in the slightest while his partner was
still alive.
When he returned to his own Macedonia
and was in position to seize power from
his rivals in the Macedonian royal
family, he started to put these the
principles he had learned as a teenager
into practice.
He organized the companions, the
traditional supporters of the Macedonian
king. He made sure that they had
consistent armor and weapons. He made
sure they trained regularly. He made
sure they had loyalty to him and no
other.
The annual levies of troops from the
population of Macedonia
were again organized.
350 years after Alexander's death,
Plutarch, the Greek historian, carefully
studied surviving documents from
Alexander's reign to write an account of
his age. of the birth of Alexander. He
wrote,
>> "Philip had just taken the city of Petia
when he received three messages.
First, that Palmano, his general, had
defeated the Alyrians in a great battle.
Second, that a horse of his had won a
race in the Olympic Games.
Third, that his son Alexander had been
born."
He was overjoyed at the news and even
more so when his soothsayer told him
that a son who was born at the same time
as three victories would be invincible
to the young Alexander growing up at PA.
Stories of his father's continuing
military successes must have been both
an inspiration and a challenge. His
tutors placed great emphasis on the
development of marshall prowess and
physical endurance. Alexander and his
companions would spend many long hours
learning such skills. Already the
fiercely competitive streak that would
spur his ambition on was clear in
Alexander's behavior. Only victory was
good enough.
King Philip wished his son to have the
culture of an educated Athena. Alexander
learned to sing and play the liar. His
love of music would later sustain him on
campaign. He learned to read and his
love of poetry would later be reflected
in his generous patronage of artists and
writers.
Alexander also learned the art of public
speaking. Again, he learned quickly and
well, he would be equally at home
yarning with his soldiers or formally
receiving foreign dignitaries. To
complete his education, his father even
hired a pupil of Plato's Academy.
Philillip had seen how self-willed his
son was and that although it was
difficult to influence him by force, he
could be persuaded to do his duty by an
appeal to his reason.
So he made a point of trying to guide
his son by persuasion rather than
orders.
He considered that the job of educating
his son was far too important for the
ordinary run of teachers. It needed in
Sophocles words guidance and restraint.
So he summoned Aristotle.
>> Aristotle was a philosopher with an
enthusiastic and wide-ranging intellect.
Alexander's natural curiosity was
expanded by his tutor. It was to stay
with him until his death. Besides his
intellectual progress, Aristotle was to
be responsible for an even more
significant influence on his young
pupil. Aristotle introduced Alexander to
Homer's epic poem of the siege of Troy,
the Iliad.
For Alexander, this work had special
significance. Achilles, one of his
heroes, was an ancestor of his through
his mother's family.
Alexander identified strongly with this
warrior adventurer.
Achilles chose a short glorious life and
eternal fame over a long peaceful life
and obscurity.
Throughout his own short glorious life,
Alexander would seek to emulate him. He
even slept with a copy of Homer's epic
under his head on campaign.
At the age of 16, Alexander's life
changed forever.
Infuriated by a plot between Athens and
thieves against Macedonia, King Philip
prepared to go on the offensive,
Alexander was entrusted with governing
Macedonia in his father's absence.
Sensing the moment to be ripe, some of
the powerful border tribes in Macedonia
rebelled.
How could a mere boy hope to subdue
them? But they had chosen the wrong boy.
Alexander speedily gathered a small
strike force. He marched against them
before they could organize their troops
and he defeated them.
Emulating his father, he established a
military outpost and named it not in
honor of his father but of himself,
Alexandria. It was to prove an ominous
portent.
Despite the young man's vanity and
pleased by his son's efforts, King
Philip educated his son the command of
the Macedonian heavy cavalry. It was to
prove an inspired move.
At the battle of Charania, Alexander led
a thunderous charge at the crucial point
of the battle.
By the defeat of the Athenian and
thieven forces ranged against them,
Philip finally united the city states
under his captain generalship.
With his borders secured and his enemies
at home defeated, Philip now prepared
for a more ambitious project, the long
awaited campaign against the hated
Persians.
As a great king, Philip was blessed with
many of the analytical skills which were
crucial to survive in those far-off
days.
Consequently, the young Alexander's
military successes and obvious ambition
did not produce blind admiration from
his father.
Philip became convinced that if he
marched against Persia, his son might
usurp him at home. Equally, Alexander
was terrified his father would confer
the succession on a future son and deny
him his divine right.
His mother, Queen Olympius, sided
jealously with her son. Philip decided
to put her aside and take a new wife. At
a banquet at which father and son drank
heavily, insults were exchanged, and
swords drawn. Alexander and his mother
left Pella for exile.
King Philip, as promised, dispatched his
army into Asia Minor, but Alexander was
not with them. Deprived of political
influence, he could only wait nervously
from his unhappy exile.
Worse still, the king had taken a new
wife who gave birth to a son.
Alexander's worst fears seemed to be
about to come true.
In 335 BC, with his final preparations
for his Persian campaign in place,
Philip arranged a marriage for his
daughter. Naturally, Alexander and his
mother were invited to attend the
extravagant wedding celebrations.
It must have been a fraught reunion, but
none could have expected the outcome
with the possible exception of two
people.
On the second day of the marriage
festivities, King Philip was brutally
assassinated by one of his own
bodyguards. In the chaos that followed,
members of the army stepped forward,
proclaiming that the king was dead and
the young Alexander be proclaimed king.
Alexander was duly declared king by the
army.
>> There is certainly no sufficient
evidence to demonstrate in a court of
law that Alexander connived with his
mother in order to murder his father.
Though of course one wouldn't expect
that because we don't have a court of
law that can get at the evidence. The
only reason for supposing that Alexander
may have connived with his mother is
that Alexander and his mother both
certainly derived advantage from
Philillip being killed at the time when
he was because Philillip just two years
before his murder had married a new wife
and that new wife was likely to produce
a new heir to the throne and so
Alexander himself was as it were a
declining asset. Once the alternative
heir to the throne uh came to be as old
as uh as Alexander now was, it was
likely enough that Alexander would be
removed from his current position as the
expected heir. So although there is some
ground for supposing that it might have
been to Alexander's advantage to ensure
with his mother that his father was
killed, there is no evidence whatever
that he was actually involved. Though of
course it is perfectly easy to argue
that as king as soon as Philillip was
was killed, Alexander was perfectly
capable of getting rid of any evidence
that there might have been.
>> Once the news of the king's murder
spread, the delicate peace he had
engineered swiftly collapsed.
Widespread insurrections followed as the
various states tried to break free.
Alexander was swift to march against the
rebel states. With astonishing speed, he
outmaneuvered his enemies. Wisely, they
gave in and recognized his authority.
Nonetheless, as soon as he moved north,
Athens and thieves once more plotted
against him. The people of thieves rose
up in revolt against their Macedonian
garrison.
Furious at their treachery, Alexander
showed for the first time his ruthless
iron streak.
Determined to teach the city states the
price of continued resistance, he
decided to make an example of one of
them. The city of thieves would suffer
the fate that had befallen the city of
Troy. It would die by fire and sword.
But it was no easy victory. The Theans
fought bravely and well, but their
courage brought them no favors from the
resolute Alexander. The prisoners were
massacred where they stood, and the city
was stormed, plundered, and burned to
the ground.
Alexander's main aim in this was to
terrify the rest of the Greek states
into submission. In this, he succeeded.
War, after all, is merely an extension
of politics by other means.
As for the people of thieves, he spared
only the priests. The rest, some 20,000,
were sold into slavery. The dead
numbered 6,000. Never again would
Alexander's authority be challenged in
Greece.
Now that thieves was merely a smoking
ruin, Athens quickly saw sense and paid
homage to Alexander.
From now on, Alexander would have the
tacit support of the city states as well
as their undying hatred.
However, with the citystates subdued for
the present, Alexander turned his
considerable talent to the Persian
enterprise. It was to be his life's
work.
>> Alexander, we call him the great, and he
really earned that title when you
consider he was born in 356 BC. At the
age of 20 in 336 BC when his father
Philip was assassinated he took over
Macedonia as the king and he took over
Philip's cause Philip II his father's
cause fighting against Persia. Alexander
brought the Greeks together in what one
might call a holy war against Persia.
And it is quite incredible that a young
man could have such such a charisma that
elderly generals would follow him. And
they did and his soldiers.
>> His officers were eager to march in a
crusade to liberate Asian Greeks and
avenge the humiliation of Athens.
But none of them could have guessed how
far their king would take them in the
pursuit of his glory.
He would lead them past the edge of the
known world.
>> He was with anything. He was the fake
attacker always. He was attached to
attack attack. No matter what the
dangers, he would always take these
tremendous risks.
>> Alexander's grand strategy was
straightforward and direct. His army was
compact, mobile, well-trained, and well
led. His enemy's territory and resources
of manpower were vast.
Alexander could succeed only if he could
lure the Persian army into battle on his
terms.
If he could kill or capture the great
king Das, he could force the succession
in his favor and the Persian Empire
would be his. With it went the advent of
wealth and power.
The prospect was daunting, but Alexander
never doubted his ultimate victory. A
victory which was to flow from his
undoubted military genius.
Alexander's campaign against the Persian
king Das was a model of precision
sprinkled with innovation and a great
slice of luck.
Granicus. Alexander outmaneuvered the
Persians by a daring night march and
river crossing. He then defeated them by
tricking them into weakening their
center and then leading a wedge of
cavalry into them at the decisive
moment.
At the battle of Isis, after marching 70
miles in two days in heavy rain,
Alexander faced an enemy in a strong
defensive position. He personally led a
magnificently successful charge against
Das's left wing and then fought
desperately to reach King Das through
the melee.
As Alexander's army held on for their
very survival, their leader bludgeoned,
fought, and hacked his way towards the
golden chariot of the great king. Dias
in danger of capture bolted from the
field, and as news of his flight spread,
his army was routed.
The crowning military victory of
Alexander's career was to be fought on
October 1st, 331 BC on the plane of
Gagamera. Outnumbered in cavalry by
almost 5 to1, Alexander was able to
force Das to attack him where he wanted.
Gagamela shows some of Alexander's great
strengths as a general and perhaps also
some of his weaknesses. He has at least
one major advantage when he goes into
battle. The Persian troops have been
kept on guard overnight so that the
Greek troops are at least fresher than
the Persians. He has however two major
disadvantages. First of all, he's
heavily outnumbered by the Persians and
this leads to the danger of his troops
being outflanked which would be fatal.
Secondly, the Persians are going to try
to rely on their scythe chariots to go
through the center of the Greek line.
Alexander had to solve both these
problems and he does it brilliantly.
First of all, he shows his technical
acumen by putting flank guards at the
side of his armies so that he can't be
outflanked. He also has a second line of
infantry behind his first line who can
turn around 180 degrees and face the
rear if the Persian troops do get around
the sides of his army to try to attack
from the rear. As regards the side
chariots, he solves this problem by
having his troops open their lines as
they come through and using specialized
javelin throws to pick them off after
they've gone through the lines. However,
this only solves his negative problems
and doesn't actually help win the
battle. To do this, he launches an
attack on the right wing. Das counters
this by sending troops from his center
to that part of the battlefield.
Alexander typically uses this as his
opportunity to attack personally. He
leads his companion cavalry and other
troops towards the center of Das's line.
Das flees at this point and Alexander
pursues him. Now, this shows the man's
courage and does show some of his
strengths as a battlefield commander,
but also shows his weakness because as
he pursues Das, Alexander's own left
wing is being surrounded and is in
danger of being wiped out. And it's only
the fact that the Persian troops find
out that their leader has flown and that
he's fled the battlefield, which leads
them to disengage, which saved
Alexander's left wing and ultimately won
the day.
>> Pluto later recalled the battle.
>> Alexander spotted his enemy behind ranks
of his royal cavalry, drawn up in a deep
formation.
Duras towered clearly above the men
masked to guard the lofty chariot he
stood in. But the men panicked at the
awesome sight of Alexander charging at
them and broke and scattered.
The brave stood fast and were
slaughtered in heaps.
In this moment of extreme danger, with
the horrors of battle all around him,
the king abandoned his chariot and his
armor, mounted his horse, and rode away.
Alexander's general ship at Galama is
not very different from his generalship
in most of his major battles. Uh most of
his major battles were fought in ways in
which the Macedonian fallank was
designed to keep the enemy in play while
the Macedonian cavalry was able to uh to
puncture the enemy line at points which
the general Alexander himself believed
to be particularly appropriate in the
given circumstances of the battle. And
so the battle began by the two sides uh
reaching each other and conducting
standard uh standard infantry warfare.
Uh what Alexander was able to do in this
and in all his battles was as cavalry
commander to observe the precise point
in the battle at which it would be
advantageous to use the cavalry charge.
Alexander appears to have done it
extremely effectively in all his
battles, his land battles, Galama
included. Galama was more difficult than
many of the others precisely because
this was the major uh force of the
Persian king uh and it was fought in the
heartlands of the Persian Empire. But
Alexander was still able to exploit his
marvelous capacity to observe the right
moment for cavalry attack. That's what
he did and he won.
This great general ship and an almost
insatiable appetite for conquest took
Alexander and his troops all over the
known world
to North Africa through great deserts
and onto Egypt, the mystical home of the
pharaohs.
It's a sobering thought, but The
pyramids of Egypt were already ancient
when Alexander stood and pondered in
their shadow.
He may well have been thinking of the
problems associated with siege warfare.
Alexander's genius was not confined to
the battlefield. He was also an expert
at laying siege to fortified cities.
This art demanded great organizational
abilities to combine the efforts of
engineers, pioneers, soldiers, and in
the case of ports, the navy to
successfully blockade and reduce a
garrison.
At the siege of Ty, despite strong
natural obstacles, well constructed
defenses, and dogged resistance,
Alexander faced all difficulties with
imagination.
The island fortress of Ty was thought
impregnable. In a seven-month siege,
Alexander assaulted it by land and sea,
blockaded it, and constructed a causeway
to connected to the mainland.
Despite atrocious weather, which
scattered his ships and savage
counterattacks from his enemies,
Alexander's exhausted men eventually
batted their way in. As usual, their
king was among the first over the wall.
But such conspicuous personal leadership
had its own price. In the course of his
career, Alexander was badly wounded nine
times, and on several occasions, his
life was only saved by the swift actions
of his friends.
In his drive to emulate Achilles, he
never flinched from risking his person
in combat.
In battle, he always tried to search out
the enemy commanders and engage them,
often with deadly results for his
opponents.
Alexander was never afraid to inspire
his men by leading from the front.
Inevitably, he suffered to the thrill of
being where the danger was. Inevitably,
glory at its cost.
Come on.
Alexander must be considered the
greatest military man of all period. The
sheer abilities of this young man who
was only going to die at the age of 33.
Would you believe he was in then the
greatest part of the world as it was
then known and he took this army of his
troops of a very small number basically
40,000 50,000 various numbers and he was
facing enemies literally hundreds of
thousands of opponents and yet he was
going to win win and win I wouldn't say
he's been the first great uh soldier of
this particular period is a certain one
who really seized upon the whole idea of
propaganda and building his own history
as he wanted it to be.
>> On campaign, Alexander took a staff of
writers, historians, and poets with him.
After all, a new Achilles needed a new
Homer. His efforts certainly worked. The
stories of his youth and his campaigns
kept his memory alive.
But the legend of Alexander has made the
real Alexander an elusive figure,
particularly as each episode of
Alexander's life was recorded and
possibly finished to show a link with
past heroes and a promise of future
glories.
One of the most famous and enduring
stories of the boy Alexander was his
taming of the wild stallion who would be
his favorite horse for 20 years.
Ephilus.
The young Alexander watched a succession
of riders being thrown by a black horse
whose face was marked with a white
flash. Only Alexander had the ingenuity
to notice that the horse was terrified
of its own shadow.
Alexander turned towards the sun,
soothed it, and then leapt on its back.
In recognition of his skill, the horse
was presented to him and a long
association begun.
Eucusphilis carried Alexander across
deserts, mountains, and rivers. And
through his greatest battle, when the
old waror eventually succumbed,
Alexander named an Indian city
in memory of his faithful, fearless
companion.
It was by such stories that biographers
of Alexander such as Plutarch tried to
explain his genius. Plutarch recorded
that on the occasion of a visit by
Persian ambassadors,
Alexander talked freely with them and
completely captivated them, not only by
his pleasant manner, but because he did
not bore them with childish questions,
but inquired about how far they had
traveled, the conditions in Persia, the
character of their king, his experience
in war, and the military strengths of
the Persian army. The ambassadors left
convinced that King Philip's celebrated
astuteness was nothing in comparison to
his son's inquiring intellect and grand
ambitions.
Other incidents keenly recorded by his
biographers supported the belief held by
many of Alexander's contemporaries that
Alexander was marked out by the gods.
Pluto recorded an account of one such
famous event
>> at Gordium in the ancient palace of King
Midas. Here Alexander first saw the
celebrated Gordium knot. By the legend
the fates had declared that whoever
untied this knot would become ruler of
the world.
But the fastenings were coiled around
each other in such a cunning way that
the ends were hidden. No man had ever
succeeded in untying the knot.
Alexander
was perturbed as to what he should do.
But as a man of action, he soon undid
the tangle by slicing through it with
his sword.
Ancient prophecies, strange omens,
miraculous occurrences. As Alexander's
conquests progressed and his fame grew,
so did the belief among his enemies that
he was godlike.
Alexander's personal belief in his
divinity became an issue that would
divide his followers. To his fellow
Macedonians, it was an excuse for him to
distance himself from them. To the
Egyptians who enthroned him as their
pharaoh, his divinity was obvious by his
victories.
For a successful young man, weighed down
by such tribulations and convinced from
birth of his right to rule, he was
remarkably astute, constantly surrounded
by flattering tongues. The temptations
towards rash behavior must have been
great.
But Alexander was always careful to
observe religious protocol and
tradition. As he passed through the
Persian Empire, Egypt, and India, he
always protected local temples, and
honored local gods. Behind his courtesy,
there were other reasons to woo the
support of priests and nobles in his
conquered domains.
But he was a marvelous statesman because
he was going across territories which
for centuries had fought against each
other. He bound them together by his
statesmanship by being very clever in
many instances leaving the people who
were previously in charge if you like to
run the shop because they trusted him
and he trusted them. And that was the
key point to it. And not least by his
coinage, the coins of Alexander the
Great, you might call the first
international coinage.
>> One of the immediate results of
Alexander's victory over Duras at
Goamela was that he was able to take
control of the royal treasuries within
the palaces and temples of Babylon,
Percepilus, and Souza. Alexander
discovered fabulous wealth. For a
general who had started his campaign
with enough funds to sustain it for less
than a month, the change in his fortunes
was incredible.
The great king's wealth was used to pay
off Alexander's Greek soldiers and then
rehire them at huge expense. Despite
this, Alexander was still rich enough to
indulge in other projects.
Like his father, Alexander measured the
extent of his territory with settlements
named after himself.
Alexandropolis was the first, but the
most famous would be the city of
Alexandria, built on an itsmouth by the
Nile Delta. Constructed in the shape of
a Macedonian cloak, it was planned on a
massive scale with broad boulevards,
marketplaces, palaces, and temples. It
was claimed that Alexander himself
designed the fortified walls. Alexandria
ensured his immortality.
But with the restless energy that
typified his life, Alexander had moved
on almost as soon as building began.
Alexandria, Alexandria the Great, you
might call it, which was the first of
his great foundations on the north coast
of Egypt. That became one of the most
sensitive, one of the most one of the
greatest centers of learning of the
ancient world. And there were some 22 or
23 other cities founded throughout the
then known world named after Alexander.
But Alexandria itself gives us so much
that we have today. We talk about
museums. We talk about libraries. The
great library at Alexandria was famed
throughout antiquity.
Scholars went there to research. The
museon, the home of the muses, gives us
the origin of our word museum.
>> Restlessness was a trait that never left
him. It could be argued that he was more
interested in conquering new territories
than ruling the ones he had. It was
certainly true that having embarked on
the Persian campaigns, Alexander's
interest in the narrow-minded politics
of Greece waned.
He exhibited no sentimental attachment
to his birthplace, and this was clear to
his subordinates. As Plutarch wrote, he
believed if the traditions could mix and
fuse together, his role would be more
established when he went far away, as it
would be based on goodwill, not force.
For this reason, he selected 30,000
Persian boys and ordered they should
learn Greek and Macedonian battle
tactics.
But Alexander was first and foremost a
soldier. He lived for conquest. And it
was this insatiable thirst that drove
him and his army ever onwards. The death
of Das and the capture and execution of
his successor elevated Alexander to the
throne of the Persian Empire as well as
a unified Greece. He was now master of
all he surveyed. But Alexander still
wasn't satisfied.
It was now that he began to talk of his
greatest ambition. And when men heard
it, they thought he had gone mad.
Alexander planned to conquer India with
an army of his own creation. The
atmosphere among his veterans became
more and more strained. There were
sporadic mutinies, but Alexander held
them together by the force of his
charismatic personality and the great
adventure got underway.
Even today, India seems far away. this
in an age of jets and airline travel. To
the ancient Greeks, it was a different
world.
>> It's a long distance to cover. If you
can imagine having to to walk every mile
of that distance from Europe uh to
India, you can begin to understand the
magnitude of what he achieved. But it
was not only that. All the way to India
and all the way back, he managed to keep
his army together as a coherent fighting
force. And that was the thing more than
anything that that made it such a
triumph.
Not just walk but fight too. Surely here
was the proof of Alexander's greatness.
For not only did he take his army to
India, he maintained its cohesion as a
fighting force. Kept it supplied, fed,
and clothed. But at times it was a
superhuman effort.
The Indian campaign was the hardest of
all Alexander's military ventures. The
climate and landscape was savage.
untraveled jungles, rivers half a mile
wide, burning deserts, freezing
mountains. The resistance he met was
more determined and fierce.
In pitch battles, Alexander's failances
faced a new and nightmarish enemy, the
Indian war elephant. Even the elements
conspired against him. Pluto's account
of the battle of Jellum dwells on the
difficulties Alexander faced. He was
overwhelmed by a great rainstorm with
terrible thunder bursts and lightning
flashes. Despite a number of his men
being struck down by lightning, he
continued to advance.
The ground had become broken and
slippery, impossible for his men to hold
their footing on. But Alexander rode on
ahead of his cavalry. Porus attacked him
with his whole army. Remembering the
threat of the elephants and their
greater number, Alexander attacked their
left. The Indian army was routed and
fell back upon their own elephants. The
Indians rallied and stubborn fights
started.
After eight long hours, the enemy was
broken.
The experience of battle and the
atrocious conditions finally broke the
spirit of Alexander's men more surely
than defeat. After 17,000 m, they had
reached the end of their endurance.
Confronted with their silent ranks,
Alexander could not even move them with
threats, promises, or bribes. The time
had come to go home. Summoning his
fleet, Alexander embarked his troops and
sailed for the mouth of the Invis.
It was almost as if his personal high
water mark had been reached. He turned
for home, his dream unfulfilled.
He began to drink heavily, bored with
the ordinary business of policing an
empire. The strain of years of leading
by example was showing. After one
particularly heavy drinking bout,
Alexander collapsed with a fever. He
held on to life for 10 days. At the end,
his distraught followers asked their
dying leader to whom he left his
kingdoms. To the strongest, he replied.
He died on June 10th, 323 BC.
The legacy of Alexander the Great is
still with us because not only did he
conquer the whole of the then known
world, he founded a new world. Up until
the time when he became king, we refer
to the period as Helenic. After
Alexander, we call it Henistic. And
indeed, we use that term to describe art
and the coinage, all sorts of things. It
becomes a chronological indicator and an
artistic indicator because he had
brought together this world and he his
legacy as such is the fact that he took
Greek culture to the ends of the earth.
There were Greek cities founded in
Afghanistan
and then of course the whole thing
fragmented in 323 BC when he died of
fever of Babylon.
The generals had no one to hang on to.
They weren't the statesman that he was.
Some were. Tommy went to Egypt and
founded a kingdom there. Others fought
amongst themselves, gradually killed
themselves off. And that was the end of
the great empire of Alexander. Then an
empire that encompassed the whole of the
then known world.
The man who left behind an empire dotted
with settlements that bore his name was
laid to rest in his greatest city,
Alexandria.
For all his accomplishments, he would be
remembered most for his military feats.
The Roman emperors Augustus and Julius
Caesar would try to emulate him. His
strategies would be studied by military
tacticians for centuries. His campaigns
would be the blueprint for Napoleon's
designs on world domination. In the
hands of Alexander the Great, the making
of war had become an art. World history
would never be the same.